People seem really uncomfortable with
the idea of human brain tissue
transplants which have been done since
the 80s and they were reasonably
successful. It just stopped in part
because of the optics and we'll talk
about it. This was a really exciting
paper. This is where they grew tiny
human brains of brain organoids and put
them into stroke induced monkeys. And
you guys are probably familiar with the
brain organoids. You can now grow human
brain organoids just from regular cells
rather than having to harvest them. In
the 80s they tried whole tissue
transplants. They were from brain tissue
from pregnancies that did not make it to
term. There were some mixed results.
Some people saw amazing improvement and
some people had other issues when the
tissue did not take it didn't
vascularize. Now, of course, what we as
humanity has learned since we started
doing stem cell transplants is that
whole tissue does better. There's been
loads of clinical trials just trying to
take stem cells, put that in a damaged
organ, and it just doesn't work. The
cells need to be in a population of like
critters that have already
differentiated in order to establish
themselves, and that makes a lot of
sense. Yes, getting mixed results did
play into the ending of this kind of
research. It also had a lot to do with
the public discourse around it. It was
easier to sell using stem cells rather
than whole tissue transplants. Now, my
own grandfather perished of Parkinson's,
and I come to find that we've had
effective treatments for nearly half a
century, but we don't do them because it
makes people uncomfortable. You can in
fact get all those fetal stem cells and
grow them when they did not come from a
fetus. It just requires, you know,
making brain organoids. We are at the
precipice of this field just exploding
when it comes to medical applications.
We've seen retinal organoids. We've seen
other organoids transplanted into
patients. It's just the brain organoids
that seem to make people really
uncomfortable. Even though the research
has shown a great amount of success for
Parkinson's as well as for stroke, which
this would be the first time stem cells
were really effective at treating
strokes ever, and it's been seen again
and again with different research
groups, give us the brain organoids. Of
course, one major barrier to actually
using brain organoids really is public
perception. Now, we can't just jump
right into human trials, and that's a
huge barrier for brain organoids because
of headlines like this. first monkey
human hybrid embryo reignites debate
over hybrid animals. Yeah, people
actually do this a lot. Usually not in
the US because of, you know, laws, but
you can make humanized embryos. You can
take stem cells from a person, inject it
into an embryo, and those cells will
grow as part of the animal. I've talked
about the one where they did it in mice
and the mice were actually more
intelligent. And of course, we do have
to use human organoids. Even for the
mouse trials, if they're ever going to
be applicable to humans, we have to
start with humans because if we were to
just start with the initial animal, like
mice or monkeys, those cells are likely
not to behave the same way as ours. So,
this is the best shot at getting
something that is applicable to people.
It has been argued that if we are going
to be using humanized animals at all in
research that we should treat them at a
higher moral threshold than we would for
non-humanized animals. That actually
bothers me because shouldn't we be
treating all animals as though they have
inherent value? Shouldn't we be trying
to reduce harm? But the idea that
humanized mice are more intelligent than
non-humanized mice is concerning just a
little bit. I do think we also have the
consideration of the level of
intelligence, but animals have not been
treated well in research forever. That's
one of the reasons I didn't go into
animal research because I can't do it. I
would be trying to take them all home. I
did have a roommate in grad school that
took animals home with her. If they were
just going to be sacrificed, she'd just
take the mice home. On a positive note
for organoids, yes, eye diseases have
been treated with retinal organoids that
are grown for that patient. Now, of
course, you might ask, "But GT, if
retinal organoids were grown for the
patient, where do brain organoids come
into play?" Right there. That's the
offtarget tissue that would have been
the neural tissue that did not turn into
the eye organoid that was used in a
patient. This can cure blindness. It's
incredible. We are so close. And yeah,
there's a lot of ethical conversations
that absolutely should be had, but this
technology is going to do a lot of good
for humanity. We shouldn't just sherk it
because it's, you know, a little bit
creepy. What do you think? Are you
excited for this technology or is the
ick factor just too